Guide to the University Commission on Women Records
University of Houston Libraries
University Commission on Women Records
1999-2010
2004-2009
02/2012-008
University of Houston. University Commission on Women
1.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes materials related to the University Commission on Women (UCW). The majority of the materials included in the collection revolve around the governance and operation of the organization with a large series being dedicated to the mentoring program. The collection consists of six series: Governance, Meetings, Mentoring Program, Reports, Research, and General Information.
Historical Note:
On September 24, 1999, then University of Houston President, Arthur K. Smith, appointed twenty-four university affiliated women to the Presidential Commission on the Status of Women for a two-year period in an effort to address the issues and concerns of women on the university campus. Two months later, at the request of the commission, President Smith expanded the commission to thirty-five members, including males and other identified persons. The following year work groups were formed and consultants began gathering information on the status of women at the University of Houston. The Committee on the Status of Women (CSW) also proposed the formation of a Women’s Resource Center (WRC) to President Smith who deferred his final decision on the proposal until the commission’s final report. On September 21, 2001 the Final Report with executive summary was forwarded to President Smith.
In 2002 Kathy Anzivino and Anne Jacobson were elected as co-chairs of the commission and committees began work on specific recommendations including the process of creating a single, permanent, campus wide advisory group on women's issues at the university. The University Commission on Women became a permanent organization in May of 2003 upon President Smith’s approval of the bylaws recommended for its operations. On January 12, 2004 the commission held its first official meeting.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. University Commission on Women
Genre/Form of Material:
Agendas (administrative records); Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes; Reports
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
UH Women's Resource Center Records (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=535)
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes materials related to the University Commission on Women (UCW). The majority of the materials included in the collection revolve around the governance and operation of the organization with a large series being dedicated to the mentoring program. The collection consists of six series: Governance, Meetings, Mentoring Program, Reports, Research, and General Information.
Detailed List of Contents
- Governance, id139697
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of material related to the operation of the University Commission of Women. Included are bylaws, a brief history of the UCW, as well as information regarding scholarships and members.
  - By-Laws, 2003; id139707 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee Members, 2003-2005; id139708 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee Members, 2006-2008; id139709 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee Members, 2009-2010; id139710 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2001, 2004, 2006-2009; id139711 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financials, 2005-2010; id139712 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goals & Recommendations, undated; id139713 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History, undated; id139714 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Officer Ballot, 2010-2011; id139715 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Planning Materials, 2010; id139716 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Priorities, 2008; id139717 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Resolutions, undated; id139718 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scholarships, 2009-2010; id139719 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sub-Committee, 2001, 2009; id139720 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Meetings, id139698
  This series contains materials related to the meetings of the UCW. The second sub-series consists of meeting materials as well as other materials distributed during the meetings. The third sub-series contains only meeting minutes.
  - Agendas, id139703
    - March-November 2004, id139722 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 2005-2006, id139723 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - January-November 2007, id139724 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - January-December 2008, id139725 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - January-December 2009, id139726 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - February-July 2010, id139727 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Meeting Materials, id139704
    - First Meeting, October 1999; id139729 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - November 1999, id139730 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - March-April 2000, id139731 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - June 2000, id139732 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - July 2000, id139733 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - August 2000, id139734 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - September 2000, id139735 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - December 2000, id139736 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - February-March 2001, id139737 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - May 2001, id139738 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - August 2001, id139739 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - September 2001, id139740 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Meeting with President Renu Khator, February 19, 2009; id139741 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes, id139705
    - February-July 2004, id139743 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - February-April 2005, id139744 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - January, September-October 2006, id139745 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 2007, id139746 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - 2008, id139747 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - 2009, id139748 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - February-July 2010, id139749 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Mentoring Program, id139699
  The materials contained in this series relate to the UCW mentoring program. The UCW established the program after conducting a study on the need for mentoring in 2004. The program was designed to help mentors and mentees develop to their full professional potential and provide economic benefits to the University of Houston.
  - “An Implementation Study”, 2007; id139751 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2009; id139752 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Evaluation/ Survey, 2007-2008; id139753 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Focus Groups, 2004; id139754 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Junior Female Faculty Focus Group, 2004; id139755 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Mentee Application Form, undated; id139756 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - “Mentoring for Results”, 2000; id139757 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - “Mentoring in a Higher Education Environment”, undated; id139758 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Mentoring Style Indicator, undated; id139759 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Objectives and Agenda, undated; id139760 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Program Matches, undated; id139761 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Survey, 2004; id139762 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Proposal, 2006-2007; id139763 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Staff Protégé Application, undated; id139764 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Subcommittee Meeting, November 2006; id139765 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - “Train Mentor-Protégé Partners and Trainers”, 2004; id139766 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Various, undated; id139767 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Reports, id139700
  This series consists of reports conducted by the UCW. Included are reports on child care, domestic partner benefits and executive summaries. Of importance is the Report on the Status of Women from October 2007, the first conducted by the UCW.
  - Annual Report, 2005-2006; id139770 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Attachments, 1999; id139771 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Child Care Center, 2001-2008; id139772 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Domestic Partner Benefits, May 2010; id139773 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Domestic Partner Benefits, October 2010; id139774 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Drafts, 2001; id139775 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Drafts, Spring 2007; id139776 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Executive Summary, March 2001; id139777 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Executive Summary, March 2001; id139778 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Executive Summary, 2001; id139779 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Executive Summary, May 2005; id139780 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Extension of the Probationary Period for Childbirth or Adoption, 2006; id139781 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - FY04 End of Year, 2003; id139782 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Final Report, September 21, 2001; id139783 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Report on the Status of Women, October 2007; id139784 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Response, June 2000; id139785 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Response, 2001; id139786 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Response, January 2002; id139787 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Response, 2008; id139788 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Survey Sub-Committee, 2007; id139789 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Research, id139701
  This series contains research materials of the UCW. Included are surveys as well as statistics concerning the University of Houston and comparable educational institutions.
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2000-2001; id139791 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Campus Environment Survey, 2007-2009; id139792 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Climate Survey, 2007; id139793 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fact Sheets, 2007; id139794 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Statistics, 2005-2010; id139795 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- General Information, id139702
  This series consists of materials related to the UCW that do not fit into the previous series. Included are articles pertaining to the UCW, organizational brochures, and information related to Jeanneret Associates, a consulting firm employed by the UCW.
  - Articles, 2000, 2007-2008; id139797 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Brochures/Handouts, undated; id139798 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jeanneret Associates, 2000-2001; id139799 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Various, undated; id139800 (Box 2, Folder 17)